Nice of you to show up, Pokey.
Yeah, sorry I'm late.
Bad traffic on the 50.
Looks like the coroner's finishing up.
Talk to him, see what he's got.
- Hey, traffic got lipstick on you.
- What? Where?
Hope she gave you breakfast.
Forensics ate all the bagels.
Late and later.
What's your excuse?
It's all a journey, Lisbon.
She washed up here
sometime last night.
A jogger found her this morning
called it in.
The only identifiable mark
is that tattoo.
Coroner says she was strangled
before she hit the water.
Some tissue under her fingernails.
Might've scratched the killer.
No sign of sexual assault.
- Lisbon.
- Yeah?
- Check between her toes.
- Why?
Because I don't really want to.
- Needle marks.
- She was an addict?
Manicure but no pedicure.
Didn't want people
to see her feet.
The track marks don't seem fresh.
Maybe she got clean.
As soon as the M.E. identifies her
I want you to go and see
if she has any drug arrests
- and check out the local rehab centers.
- Yeah, you got it.
- Yeah?
- "Mr. Jane"
"this is Agent Vint Molinari,
Missing Persons."
"I'm on the Kristina Frye case."
An old client of Frye's was listening
to some psychic call-in show
on the radio the other day
heard somebody she swears
was Kristina.
"We've got a recording
of the show."
Can you tell me
if this is her voice?
"I spoke to the last
caller's late mother Susan."
"She told me she's happy"
"and wants her daughter to know
how proud of her she is."
It's her.
Did you trace the call?
Comes from a landline
house on Delmore Road
north of Fremont Landing.
"I'll let you know
if we find anything there."
Jane. How you doing?
Blood on the wall--
DNA analysis says
it's Frye's.
And the house was clean.
No prints or trace evidence of any kind.
No sign of a body or a grave.
She's alive. If he killed her,
he would've left her body out on display.
Vint, it looks like this is more than just
a missing persons case to me.
I'm gonna talk to the head of the division
and ask him to hand the case over to us.
Why? Because it's Red John
and you're the Red John guys?
I've read his file, too.
Frye's been missing
for four months.
Red John never kept a victim alive
for more than a few days.
He never left
a-a clue on the scene
except for the--the painted face.
And that call Frye made--
that's hardly a cry for help.
What's your point?
Well, who knows if Red John
had anything to do with this?
As far as I know
Frye painted the face herself.
Why would she do that?
Well, the woman thinks
she talks to the dead.
She's half a nutcase
walking out the door.
Lisbon, I-I agree
with Agent Molinari.
Kristina's case should remain
in his capable hands.
Let's, uh, not get in the way.
I don't understand.
You don't want the case?
So what are you doing?
Nothing.
Why don't we just skip the part
where you lie to me
and get right to the part where you
tell me what you're gonna do?
Red John let Kristina make
a call that could be traced.
- He's playing a game.
- With who?
See you later.
Yeah, that sounds great.
I can make it there by 7:00.
Listen, I have to go.
I'll speak to you later, okay? Bye.
If you're seeing traffic
on the 50 tonight
you think she could set
her alarm a little earlier?
Okay, look, I get it.
This is, uh...
it's the last time you have
to hear about my love life.
I don't care about your love life.
Just don't let it affect the job.
- My love life is not gonna affect--
- "Hey."
- Hey, boss.
- Anything on the girl in the river?
"Name's Celia Jovanovich."
Some convictions for narcotics
possession. No family.
What about the rehab angle?
No mention of a program
in her record.
Well, she must've cleaned up somehow.
- No arrests in almost two years.
- Hey, that tattoo on our vic--
- it's worn by members of Visualize.
- Visualize? The cult?
They do work with addicts.
She could've cleaned up there.
- See? The wings form a "v" for "Visualize".
- Yeah.
What was the name
of the guy who runs it?
Stiles. Bret Stiles.
Agent Lisbon,
I'm Brother Steven Wench.
- Mr. Jane...
- Mm.
This is Warner Vander Hoek
our Chief of Security.
- Julius Coles, our attorney.
- How do you do, agent?
Quite an impressive file
at CBI, Lisbon.
I know if anyone can find
Celia's killer, you can.
I appreciate your confidence
Mr. Vander Hoek.
How did you read my file?
I spent 11 years
working Seattle Homicide.
Seven years
in the Intelligence Division.
Ooh. That's a whole lotta cop
for a self-help group.
And we have enemies.
As Mr. Stiles says...
"The truth always does."
Where is, uh, Bret?
I'm afraid brother Stiles is busy
with church business
at the moment.
- And why are you so afraid?
- It's a figure of speech...
- Yes, it is. Shall we? Lead the way.
- Yes, we should.
"My name is Celia Jovanovich."
"This picture was taken
when I had been a heroin addict"
"for nine years."
"I had no job or home"
"no future, no hope."
"But I beat addiction
and changed my life"
"when I began to Visualize."
Our addiction counselors found her
literally living in the streets.
She attempted suicide three times.
They...
They brought her here, and...
This is what she became.
Well, she certainly became better
at doing her makeup.
Your low personal opinion
of Visualize is duly noted...
But irrelevant. Let's try and confine
our discussion to the facts.
Of course. Uh, Mr. Coles,
you're not a member here, are you?
I am not.
That's interesting
that Mr. Stiles would hire a lawyer
- outside of the sacred fold. Hmm?
- Oh, what did Celia do here?
She worked in our security section.
It's called vigilance.
We provide personal security
for the church's senior leaders.
- I was her, uh, supervisor.
- What's her home address?
She lived here. We provide homes
for members who want them.
Celia had had it tough.
The--the church was her haven.
And we're gonna need to speak
to all of her friends
- acquaintances, coworkers.
- That'll be fine
with the proviso that I or one of my
associates be present at all times.
Was there anybody in particular
that she was close to?
There was a fiancé, David Herren.
He's a member of the church
but I don't know where he is right now.
Huh.
I'm sure you'll be able
to locate him for us.
Agent, I assume you will be looking
at suspects outside the church.
I'd hate to think that this was
some sort of witch hunt.
Oh, we'll go wherever
the investigation leads us.
- So, um, thank you very much.
- Okay.
Uh, excuse me.
- Tec, interesting name.
- Yeah.
You look like an honest young man.
Do you know where Brother Stiles
is right now?
- No, sir, I don't.
- Very honest.
Terrible liar. Is--is he this way?
Or is he this way?
- Okay.
- Sir, I-I don't think that--uh, sir?
- Yeah, spit it out.
- I-I don't understand what you're doing.
You don't wanna tell me
where Stiles is
so when I move you in his location,
you react negatively.
I'm just reading
your negative reaction.
Well, please stop.
You're gonna get me in trouble.
This way?
Please don't go in there, sir.
Thank you.
"You see
if the mind is free"
"there's nothing
that you can't achieve."
"Because then the mind
has no limits."
It's a spaceship
with the power to travel across
all six dimensions.
- Journeying off to--
- Excuse me, uh, Bret?
- I have a question.
- What?
Sorry. Did somebody speak?
Uh, it--it was me.
- Patrick?
- Yeah.
How nice to see you.
Why offer only six dimensions?
Is--is it to hold off a couple
of dimensions to sell later?
I think six is quite enough.
When did you last see
Celia Jovanovich?
Oh, uh, Celia.
Yes, um, let me think. Um...
I believe she worked
a security detail for me
earlier in the week--
a seminar for pre-members
at the Hyatt.
Pre-members?
Those that have not yet seen
the truth.
You would be a pre-member.
Poor Celia.
It's tragic, uh...
She fought so hard
for her sobriety.
When did you learn
of her death?
Well, I don't know.
I suppose
when they identified the body.
You know, many policemen
are Visualize members.
What do you think
happened to her?
No idea.
You have a theory?
Oh, no.
I never theorize.
We gurus must always
speak the truth
or... nothing.
You were surprised I was here about Celia.
Why did you think I was here?
Kristina Frye, of course.
Kristina Frye?
Red John has her, right?
It's a terrible thing.
First, your wife and child
now miss Frye.
Sounds like he's jealous, Patrick.
It sounds like...
he wants to take away everything
and everyone that you care about.
It's a form of love
you know.
What do you know
about Kristina Frye and Red John?
Patrick, I like you.
I like your vim.
And Red John--
he seems to be a perfectly
unpleasant sort of fellow.
If I knew how to get you even
half a step closer to him
I would cross desert wastes
to tell you.
But I don't know.
"Avanti."
Ah, Starsky and Hutch.
Thank goodness.
Mr. Jane might have cut me
into small cubes by now.
"God is in your mind
right here."
All you have to do to see him
is clear out the bad energy.
I'll repeat the question.
Have you seen Celia Jovanovich
in the past 48 hours?
I've been visiting my mother
in Chino.
I got back this morning.
- That's all I need. Thanks.
- Aren't you interested
in the path to spiritual clarity
and personal freedom?
No.
How's it goin'?
Well, Celia was nice
and a good team member
and joining Visualize is a good idea.
That's it, pretty much.
- Keep trying. You've seen Jane?
- Yeah, he's upstairs.
Vander Hoek took him there
to see Celia's room.
- Is he okay?
- I guess. Why?
Nothing. Stiles just seems
to get to him a little bit.
- That's a neat trick.
- Yeah, I wish he'd teach it to me.
I got the fiancé's details.
David Herren works
at a restaurant downtown.
- Go talk to him.
- Okay.
You--come on. Let's talk.
Before we do, can I just ask
are you happy in your lives?
Sit down.
This was Celia's room.
Thank you.
David Herren?
- Yeah.
- Wayne Rigsby, CBI.
I need to, uh, talk to you
about Celia Jovanovich.
- Yeah, yeah. Listen, the thing is I--
- "One moment, David."
Hi. I'm Julius Coles
David's attorney.
Wow. You guys are organized.
"Us guys"? Feels prejudicial.
You have a problem
with constitutional rights?
No, sir.
I was a mess
when I heard the news.
But I remember
what Mr. Stiles says--
"Clarify the mind with discipline,
order, work."
Are you the Head Chef?
Prep chef now.
Maybe more than that someday.
How long had you been
engaged to Celia?
A couple of weeks.
And how long had you
known her before?
- I didn't... know her. I mean--
- I don't understand.
I had never seen her before.
High level Visualize members
often opt for what are called
designed marriages.
- The partners are matched for, uh...
- Energy consilience.
- So it was an arranged marriage?
- A rational marriage.
I knew the minute I saw Celia
we belonged together.
Was there someone else?
Someone angry about being replaced?
An ex-boyfriend perhaps?
Absolutely not.
How can you be so certain?
You only just met her.
Knowledge comes to those
who are open to it, agent.
I knew Celia.
There was no one else.
Are you sure?
Because Celia was strangled.
That's a killer who's upset
really wants to hurt the victim.
There wasn't anybody who
might've been mad at you and Celia?
- Might've made you mad?
- There's no need to answer that.
I'm just trying to get
the picture here.
No, you're poking at him
with wild conjecture
to see how he reacts
and I won't have it.
This is over.
So I checked into Herren.
Cooking's just a hobby.
His family's loaded--
old lumber money.
When he turns 27
he inherits 10 million.
That's probably why Stiles
arranged the marriage.
With Celia married to Herren, the church
is more likely to tap into the money.
Yeah, but it's not motive
for Herren to kill Celia.
Oh, was there anything else
from the interviews at Visualize?
Nothing useful.
They all seem so happy.
I mean, truly happy.
Yeah. It's creepy.
Jane. Kinda lost track of you
at Visualize.
Took a nap.
Is something on your mind?
No, no.
Um, I'm gonna be upstairs.
Celia had some problems
with Visualize philosophy--
questions, issues with the dogma.
She, uh, might've wanted
to talk to someone about it.
Someone outside of the church.
Someone mentioned a friend
of hers who was a member but left.
Um... Lucy Joel.
Are you sure nobody was following you,
saw you come in?
Lucy, nobody followed us.
I'm not crazy, okay?
I have been followed
and threatened.
Visualize doesn't like
when people leave the hive.
When you're a member
every week you sit down in front of a camera
and lay out every bad thing
you've done.
I mean, everything.
It's called ventilation.
Your vent vids.
It's supposed to air you out.
It makes you feel great, clean.
Then when you're leaving
they say, "Whoa."
"We know all this nasty stuff."
You're not gonna say anything
bad about Visualize, are you?
We're not here to get dirt
on Visualize.
We wanna talk about Celia.
Yeah.
She was sweet
almost too nice, you know?
She needed people
a little too much.
She knew Visualize was crazy
but they'd gotten her clean.
And she was scared
to leave, you know?
Thought she'd start using again.
Was she in touch with you?
She'd call, just to talk
bitch about the church
you know, stuff.
Was there anything specific
on her mind?
I-I can't. I'm sorry.
- Lucy, listen. We can offer you--
- I don't want any trouble. No...
It was really hard to leave that place.
Now I'm good with the church
and the church is good with me.
Everything's good.
Listen, I know you're scared
but right now
you're Celia's guardian
the only one that can help her.
It's up to you.
She was having an affair with
somebody very big in the church.
She wouldn't tell me his name.
Then she was supposed
to marry Herren.
And he was sweet
kept saying he loved her.
She felt bad lying to him.
Last time I talked to her
she said
she had to do something
but she didn't say what.
And if anybody finds out
I told you that
I am so dead.
You were great in there.
"You're Celia's guardian."
It was nice.
I lied this morning.
I do care that you're seeing
someone else.
It hurts a little.
I mean, it's no biggie.
I'll get over it.
I want us to be friends.
We can get to that point, right?
Can we be just friends?
Yeah. Sure, we can.
Good. I'd like that.
Behind us.
- Huh?
- Someone's tailing us.
- Visualize?
- Oh, yeah.
I guess Lucy isn't crazy.
Getting the plates.
- Should I pull 'em over?
- Can you get behind 'em?
Throw a loop? Easy. Watch.
Grace!
- You okay? You okay?
- Yeah, yeah. You?
- Yeah.
- I just--I just need a minute.
Go see the other guys.
Hey. CBI. You wanna tell me
what the hell you're doing?
FBI. I could ask you
the same thing.
- Agent O'Laughlin, is it?
- Craig O'Laughlin.
That's right, ma'am.
You wanna tell me why the FBI
was tailing two of my agents?
Sure.
We've been looking at Bret Stiles
and Visualize for a couple years now.
And we've had allegations of tax fraud,
racketeering and a lot worse
but we haven't gotten our hands
on anybody that could tell us
about the organization.
Tight as a drum.
Yeah, but why follow us?
My boss thinks Stiles may have people
inside law enforcement
which would explain why we're not
getting anywhere with the investigation.
Y-you think that we're working
with Visualize?
She wanted us to look
into the possibility. That's all.
And I've seen no evidence of it.
What you did was reckless.
I should bring you up
for departmental discipline.
But he shouldn't have been following you
so I'm gonna let it pass.
And you tell your boss
if she wants to catch bad guys
she should follow bad guys.
It was a pleasure working
with the FBI.
Hey, listen. I'm sorry about that.
Does it hurt?
No. No, it's not that bad.
Thanks.
You know, Van Pelt...
You--you related
to Amos Van Pelt, by any chance?
The football coach at Burton?
He's my father.
Whoa. Uh, he's one hell of a coach.
I was a wide receiver
at U. of M.
Your, uh, your dad gave us
one tough game.
O'Laughlin...
Didn't you go NFL?
Tennessee.
I did, yeah.
Yeah, just a couple of years.
Thanks for remembering.
Anyway, I should get back to the office
get beat up by my own boss.
You see your dad
tell him he's remembered.
I will. Thanks.
Yeah.
Hey. Excuse me.
You're the FBI guy, right?
I'm a special agent in charge
if that's what you mean.
Now, that's exactly
what I mean.
So you guys are
investigating Visualize
and this character
Bret Stiles, right?
I guess that's common
knowledge by now.
Yeah. Do you have a guy
deep inside the church?
You know, un-undercover agent?
You can't seriously
be asking me that.
So that's a "yes".
Any chance of a name?
No. No chance.
We have to get back
to Visualize.
Why is that?
Celia Jovanovich was almost
certainly killed by her lover
so she almost certainly
mentioned his name
in her vent video.
Ergo, we need
to see her videos.
I'll get my coat.
What do you have in there?
Oh, look at that.
Thank you.
"To make ourselves
fully conscious"
"the challenge is
to expand the power of mind"
"by dispelling doubt and guilt
so that we may find in our--"
Sorry. Didn't mean
to startle anyone.
Well, actually, I did.
You got a minute?
What is it, Mr. Jane?
You're the FBI's
undercover agent, right?
- What?
- I need a favor.
Just a small one.
Get rid of 'em.
Guys, take a break.
I have no idea
what you're talking about.
Well, when I just popped
the bag right now
your hand went for your hip.
Like you were reaching for your gun.
It's a cop instinct.
Never goes away.
Do you have any idea
what you're doing?
This is an ongoing investigation
and I spent three years working
my way into this organization.
Hey, don't freak out, Serpico.
I need one little thing.
Forget it.
Your investigation is dead.
If I picked you out, then Stiles
has definitely picked you out.
The only reason
he hasn't gotten rid of you
is because he's using you.
He's feeding you false information.
Do you have any usable evidence?
No. Didn't think so.
And you never will.
You can help me, though.
Together, we can catch
Celia Jovanovich's killer.
What's this about?
I need to see
one of her vent videos
and I need you to take me
to where they're kept.
- Get a warrant.
- Warrants take time.
And meanwhile, back at the ranch
they're wiping the tapes.
The room where they're stored
is full of security cameras.
- They'll be on to you in minutes.
- Yes, they will.
That's what I'm talking about.
Let's go.
Ah, Agent Lisbon.
What's all this about you wanting
Celia's vent videos?
We believe Celia Jovanovich
may have identified her killer
in one of the videos.
- We'd like to take a look at 'em.
- No, no, no. That's impossible.
The ventilations show our members
at their most vulnerable.
Only senior members of the church
are allowed to see them.
I mean
I could no more show you them
than a priest could discuss
a confession.
Now, if you'll please
excuse me...
- Sir?
- Yeah.
Security feed of Patrick Jane.
What?
Agent, this is a security camera feed
from our video room.
What's going on?
It's been about half an hour.
This is outrageous.
I'm getting bored.
Mr. Stiles is calling in every
important person he knows
to try and get us fired.
It takes time.
You're done.
You are done.
We've spoken to your superiors
explained to them
that we view Mr. Jane's actions
as a grievous breach
of civil liberties.
We'll be pursuing
civil and criminal remedies.
Meh.
I'm curious.
You couldn't hope to watch
these videos for any length of time.
What did you think you'd accomplish
by coming here?
Oh, we'll see the videos.
Oh, you will see them, will you?
And--and how is that?
- You'll give them to us.
- Oh, really?
And why? Why?
Celia Jovanovich
was killed by her lover--
someone very high up
in your church
someone that is very probably
in this room right now.
Well, that's very interesting
if it were true.
And I daresay, is mentioned
in her videos.
So if you say
you'll give us the videos
the killer will identify himself.
He will be the man
that insists most forcefully
that you shouldn't give 'em
to us.
- What if I killed her?
- You?
You wouldn't hurt a fly.
Patrick has offered a very,
um, persuasive argument.
I'm going to be handing over
the videos to him.
No!
No. Absolutely n--
I-I can't allow that.
Why not?
The precedent
would be unacceptable.
It would--
it would open up all manner
of intrusive police action.
That sounds like lawyer speak
for "I did it. I did it. I'm guilty."
Mr. Coles, in a week or so,
forensics is gonna have processed
the DNA that was under
the victim's fingernails.
We're gonna need a sample
from you.
That's ridiculous. That--
that is completely unnecessary.
No, it's just a pinprick.
Doesn't hurt a bit.
Julius, please.
Tell me...
You did not kill
that young woman.
No, I didn't.
That one--that--that looked like
it did hurt. Huh?
She was a sweet girl.
I'd see her
when I came to meet Bret.
She liked to talk about the book
she was reading.
Things just went from there.
I-I was...
I was very fond of her.
And then Herren came
into the picture.
Celia said she had
to tell Herren the truth...
about us.
I told her, Visualize was
my only client.
Bret would banish me
if he knew I-I was involved
with a member.
She just kept saying
she couldn't lie.
She couldn't lie
to save my career.
I got angry.
And we fought.
It happened.
So we have a deal?
D.A. agreed--
involuntary manslaughter.
Three years with time served.
In exchange
for your cooperation
with the FBI's investigation
into Visualize and Bret Stiles.
Okay, you got it.
I look forward to working
with you, Mr. Coles.
Ah. Three years is nothing.
It's the way of the world.
He's selling Stiles. He's a big fish.
The FBI has to pay.
If you think
about this stuff too much
you'll drive yourself crazy.
That's Herren.
Gun!
"Drop it!"
- "Drop your gun!"
- "On the ground!"
Drop it! Drop it now!
Get your hands above your head!
Don't move!
Get your head down!
Head down!
I had to do something.
He killed my soulmate.
Inactivity is the sign
of the clouded mind.
- Discipline, order, work.
- Where'd you get the gun?
I stole it from the desk
of the manager.
He keeps it
for making night deposits.
Did anyone else know
what you were gonna do?
Put me in prison.
I don't care.
My heart is free.
The minute I saw him, I knew.
I did the right thing.
Did anyone else know?
No. It was my idea.
Thanks for your time.
I understand Herren confessed.
He didn't mention your name.
The poor soul.
But...
Why would he mention me?
Well...
you didn't go
and tell him to kill the man
but you clarified his options
which is as good as killing him
as far as I'm concerned.
Is that the official view?
Is this why you wanted to see me?
'Cause a phone call
would've been fine.
The FBI's given up.
Oh, that's a shame.
I rather enjoyed Brother Wench
and his clumsy machinations.
Oh, well, there it is.
You're safe.
Bravo.
Well, always nice to know
but that's not why I'm here.
It seems that your friend John
is planning a surprise party for you.
How do you know
what Red John is planning?
- It doesn't matter.
- It certainly matters to me.
How do you know
what Red John is planning?
My dear chap
I know so much more
than you or Red John
could ever imagine.
Accept this as a gift from a friend. Or not.
"Clear!"
"Clear upstairs."
- All clear.
- Clear.
Boss.
Kristina?
Kristina.
EMT said she had a puncture wound
in one arm, like from an IV.
Must be how Red John
got the blood out of her.
He also said there was
no other sign of assault--
physical, sexual, anything.
Why won't she speak?
What did he do to her?
Still nothing.
Not a sound.
Okay.
Remember this?
Come on, Kristina.
Listen, it's Jane.
You remember me.
I know you do.
What was the worst date
you ever had?
Huh?
Kristina, please.
Please stop this.
Just speak to me.
Psych personnel
are on their way.
Could be worse, you know.
She could be dead.
I guess tea
is always worth a try.
- What is he doing?
- I have no idea.
I call on the spirits.
I ask for the presence of the departed soul
of Kristina Frye.
Reveal yourself
Kristina Frye.
Can you hear me, Kristina?
I can hear you, Patrick.
Well, thank you.
Thank you
for speaking with me.
I'm so glad you called on me.
I knew in the end
you'd become a believer.
- I am not a believer.
- I hear sadness in your voice.
Don't be sad, Patrick.
Death is not the end.
The afterlife's a beautiful place.
It's peaceful here.
Happy.
You're not dead.
You're talking to a ghost
and still you're a skeptic.
You are impossible.
You're not dead, Kristina.
You're alive.
You're in denial.
Eventually, you'll accept the truth.
I know it's hard.
God knows I struggled
against it myself.
But you can't... fight... death.
How did you die?
I don't remember.
It's funny how things
become unimportant.
It's as if my life
was a dream.
I woke up.
I can't recall what happened.
Did you see Red John?
- Who?
- Red John.
Red John--the man
that abducted you.
I don't understand
what you're talking about.
Oh. Yeah. Sure.
Apparently, Bret Stiles
is out of the country.
He's opening a center in Jakarta.
Visualize people say they don't know
when he'll be back.
Figures.
Boss. We caught one.
Downtown.
Are you okay?
We're up. Let's go.